<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Englands remembrances</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38427</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3038</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3305</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12131650</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12131650</idno>
            <idno type="VID">54740</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A38427)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54740)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 593:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Englands remembrances</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>The final "s" of "remembrances" has been changed in ms. to "r"; ms. corrections and additions throughout.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Harvard University Libraries.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:54740:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>ENGLANDS REMEMBRANCES.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>MONGST ſome ſayings of a Wiſe Man, one of his beſt was, that the Life of a Life was a good Conſcience: This may be good Counſel to our fellow ſubjects of England, at this time, in this Apoſtate Age, whereas nothing, but a preſent Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition is acceptable, upon no certainty; but great uncertainties, both of death, ſudden changes, and alterations. This addreſs, and faithfull advice, is out of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and zeal, for the honour and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of the Engliſh Nation, which is as near and dear to a true wel-wiſher to his Country, as his neareſt relations; all ſufferings to a clear Engliſh heart in redemption of it, would be like a fair hot ſun ſhining day, in the end of Harveſt: For only excremental creatures, proceed, and diſſolve in the like nature: But man that is chiefly born to ſerve God, his King, and Country (upon the principles of Vertue, Juſtice, and true Religion, according to revealed knowledge) hath a duty of injunction laid upon him. The blot upon our Nation, muſt needs trouble all Engliſh hearts: The deception under the Mask of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which is now thoroughly unmasked, ought, and muſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand much Repentance: The Deſign of ſome of our Northern neighbours (with the conſpiracy of ſome of our Country men) to pull down, one Eccleſiaſtical Government (for their own intereſt) before another was put into a method, for the ſettlement of Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, hath juſtly brought this confuſion upon themſelves in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and on us in <hi>England;</hi> and do not we ſee, how God hath worn our in their own actions, and blaſted many of the Plotters of our alterations in <hi>England;</hi> although in Juſtice from Heaven we muſt look, upon our ſins, the Nations ſins, and the three Kingdoms ſins, to be the moving
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:54740:2"/>cauſe from God, ſo to puniſh us: For is there any evil in the City, and God hath not done it, <hi>Amos</hi> the 3. <hi>chap.</hi> and 6. <hi>ve.</hi> that is the evil of puniſhment which we all juſtly deſerve: Hath not God pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed the Iriſh nation, now almoſt extirpated for that horrid Maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre, Murther and Rebellion, in that Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> palliating their wickedneſs under a counterfeit Commiſſion and connivance from the laſt King, whoſe innocence was moſt traiterouſly abuſed in it, as was confeſſed, by Sir <hi>Philemon Oneal,</hi> before his execution, in preſence of divers worthy and noble perſons now living, who can te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie it upon their voluntary or required Oaths: The Kings Broad Seal being taken off from a Letters Patents for a grant of lands, and put to a forged and counterfeit Commiſsion: And concerning thoſe papers taken out of Mr. Secretary <hi>Windebants</hi> ſtudy, and put by the Parliaments order into the cuſtody of one Mr. <hi>Willingham,</hi> a Citizen of <hi>London,</hi> ſome years ſince dead, a noble Lord, and a Citizen of <hi>London,</hi> ſent his Majeſty word, that if any of thoſe papers, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Ireland,</hi> or any other of them, might do his Majeſty prejudice, (ſome perſons of the Parliament intending to lay a charge againſt his Majeſty about them) ſuch a courſe was, and ſhould be taken for their conveyance away (if his Majeſty would have it) that they ſhould never ſee light more: But the King ſent that noble Lord word, and that Citizen (who acted the buſineſs with Mr, <hi>Willingham</hi>) that he thanked them for their love and care of him; but for any knowledge that he had, or had given order in, or for that buſineſs or maſſacre of <hi>Ireland,</hi> he defied the Divel and all his Imps, or any body elſe about it, but if any of his ſervants had done amiſs, they muſt anſwer for their own faults, and this will be teſtified upon Oath before God and Man. And to confirm his Majeſties clearneſs in that buſineſs of <hi>Ireland,</hi> you ſee his enemies could not lay the leaſt imputation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Majeſty in it, although they wanted neither Will nor Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice. For <hi>Scotland,</hi> how hath God puniſhed that Nation, for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent blood and cruelties they have acted amongſt themſelves, for their perjury and falſeneſs, for the breach of their publick and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Faith, and agreement with the King, made ſolemnly in the Parliament of <hi>Scotland</hi> 1641. after full ſatisfaction given by the King in that Parliament, for that Church and kingdom, and by invading <hi>England</hi> again with an Army, contrary to their former Faith and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:54740:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>Agreement, upon the ſurruptions making, wreſting, and breaking their ſolemn League ad Covenant, conſtruing part of it to ſerve their own ſence and ends, and not taking the whole ſcope, ſence, and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of it together, (in which Covenant the Engliſh Independents out-witted them) they ſuppoſing upon the intereſt of that Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to have overſwayed the Parliament, made <hi>London</hi> their own in affection and intereſt, and ſo to have obtained the power of all <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> but with what ſucceſs hath God yet bleſſed that Covenant, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing illegally entred into, at the firſt, although much, and not all, the contents thereof is good: The Covenant Makers, being the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Breakers, who declared a publick promiſe to have the Kings approbation and confirmation of it, which was deferred, until they had a Sword to inforce and compel it, not a Chriſtian like way to ſettle Religion, which otherwiſe ſhould be by a Synod of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Divines, legally called: And for delivering their King to the Engliſh Independents, when the Plot was viſibly ſeen, for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of King and Parliament, upon the Compact and Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for receiving 200000 pounds ſterling, for their Army, when the King came to their Army, then at <hi>Newark</hi> for a Sanctuary (a Blot in Marble) whereas if they had kept the King, and not deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered him untill they had treated with the King and Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>London,</hi> ſo much longed for, and deſired, the King, Parliament, and kingdomes had been ſettled upon the Baſes of Juſtice, Truth and Righteouſnes, with a firm and laſting Peace, and a Religious and Civill Reformation, of all former errors, and although they had the publick faith of the Parliament of England, for a Treaty with his Majeſty, and both Kingdomes upon their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering the King, yet they could not but wel underſtand, by their Commiſſioners, who had lived long in England, at the coſt and charge of England, that the Independent Faction, grew ſo ſtrong in the Engliſh Parliament, and Army, which were no friends, to the King, that it could not be ſafe, for his Majeſty, to be in that cuſtody at <hi>Holmby,</hi> which was rather in the power of the Army than Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament (as it proved too ſadly afterwards) the Army being molded, contrary to the firſt Iudgment of Parliament; where as if the King had beene delivered, unto the protection of his ſubjects in <hi>London,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:54740:3"/>there was then a viſible power, and foundation, to guard his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, from the deſigne of <hi>Oliver Cromwell,</hi> whoſe deſign was well perceived by many at that time. And when the Scots had diveſted themſelves of the King, by delivering his Majeſtey over: and <hi>Oliver Cromwell</hi> was acting that unparralleld death, which could not but be wel known, (to the grand Committee of Parliament, ſitting then in <hi>Scotland</hi>) by the advice of their Commiſſioners, being then in <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> who lukewarmly declared againſt that horrid act: and ſo did the Committee of Parliament in <hi>Scotland</hi> as Lukewarmly act, at that time in <hi>Sco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>land,</hi> the Kings beſt friends there, being excluded from ſitting; but it is well knowne, what paſſed betweene <hi>Argile</hi> and <hi>Cromwell,</hi> at my Lady <hi>Humes</hi> houſe in <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> concerning the Kings death. And after the Kings horrid death, for breaking their Treaty made at <hi>Breda</hi> (fully conſented unto by this preſent King) before they would ſuffer his Majeſty, to land in <hi>Scotland,</hi> hee then lying upon their Coaſt, in great perill and danger of the Engl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh Parliament ſhips, (then near his Majeſty) whoſe deliverance, God prevented at Sea upon the coaſt, by a great miſt: and for Inforcing a Declaration, upon the now innocent King after his landing, by the power of <hi>Argile,</hi> and the Church, to take the Guilt of that kingdome upon his innocent ſelfe, and afterwards, by jubjugating his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, under the pretended power of Church Government, and <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels</hi> Creatures: For delivering up their Army, at <hi>Dunbar,</hi> (ſo much purged by the Church) by the Treachery, and Correſpondence of ſome few perſons, when <hi>Cromwel</hi> could not have ſtayed 6. Dayes longer in the country, and offered <hi>Scotland</hi> ſatisfaction, for the da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, he hed done to that kingdome, and would have left it, and returned into <hi>England,</hi> with 3. or 4. Troops of horſe: for delivering up there Forts, and Caſtles upon Treachery, and for mony. As <hi>Edenburgh</hi> caſtle, by <hi>Dundas</hi> old <hi>Leiſleyes</hi> Son in Law, and <hi>Sterling</hi> Caſtle upon conditions, to ſave their owne particular Goods, for delivering the Records of the kingdom: for their deſign at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in of Duke <hi>Hamiltons</hi> Army in Anno 1648. not for a clear in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to relieve <hi>England,</hi> and themſelves from the preſent treaſon and ſlavery then hathing by ſome compact perſons of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> but intending to have the whole power, and domination of the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:54740:3"/>whole Engliſh nation to themſelves, as it hath been clearely ſeene ſince, and confeſſed by themſelves, and God proſpered it accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly: and in the <hi>Worceſter</hi> buſineſſe, noe Engliſh power, nor Army muſt be raiſed, but under Commiſſion, and power of the Scots, and hath not God, for their ſinnes, and their only Acting the Scotch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, inſlaved them wholly to the Engliſh, and made ther Kingdome a Mercinary Province, or Commonwealth, in ſubjection unto <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> betrayed, and voluntarily ſubmitted unto, by <hi>Argile,</hi> and ſome of their country men, lately ſitting, in the late howſe of Commons in <hi>England,</hi> onely for mony, profit and their particular advantage, <hi>Scotland</hi> is never to be truſted, for the intereſt of <hi>England,</hi> unleſſe the Exchequer of <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> were greater then the Exchequer of <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter;</hi> and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Scotland</hi> were <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and is not this a greater judgment from heaven, upon <hi>Scotland,</hi> but blame not the whole nation, for many of their rulers have cauſed them to err, although the Commons, at this time (who have beene formerly, to much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaved by their Lords, and Landlords) are to much addicted to their lucre, and profit, wherein the Engliſh have indulged them, with long Leaſes, and by laying the Chief Burdens upon their Landlords, for the more quiet of that kingdome, but let Duke <hi>William Hamiltons</hi> ingenious confeſſion a little before his death, and his affection to the King, then alſo expreſſed at <hi>Worceſter</hi> to a noble Engliſh Lord, now living, and the Marqueſſe of <hi>Moniros,</hi> his and the Lord <hi>Nappiers</hi> Loyalty, and ſome other Lords in cuſtody in <hi>England,</hi> and others in <hi>Scotland</hi> upon their Parrol, have that everlaſting memory, which their blood and honors have purchaſed. And <hi>England</hi> which is now, prevalent in power, but odious, by its Governours, both at home and abroad, unleſs to ſuch, who are involved in guilt, and profit with them. If <hi>England</hi> repent not of its perjury, oppreſſion, and injuſtice, to its country men, bretheren, and of all the innocent blood, it hath ſpilt in <hi>England:</hi> for its breach of faith, ſolemnly ingaged, in and out of Parliament before God, Men, and Angels, to the whole world (witnes their declarations) and for ſuffering a compact number of conſpirators, cunningly to deceive the people under pretence of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation in Religion, and the kingdomes abuſes, who have brought in, a far greater deſtruction of Religion, then before, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:54740:4"/>all the liberties of the ſubject, inſlaving them to an abſolute illegal, and arbitrary power, and to the bloody luſt, and wils, of any perſons whatſoever, that may, or can hereafter, get, or obtayne, any unlawful power, or Government whatſoever: who have deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ancient, ſafe, healthful, and fundamentall conſtitution of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> by King, and Parliament, ad introduced varieties of mock Parliaments, to color there wickednes, and to make monſtrons Courts and conſtitutions, only to ſerve their own luſt, ambition, and Ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice, and for the enſlaving, and murthering of their fellow ſubjects, who with their Cap. General <hi>Oliver Cromwel,</hi> the grand Protectorian brooke of the perſonal Treaty, in the Iſle of Wight, with the laſt King, when his Majeſtey, had fully conſented, unto the parliaments propoſitions, and given ful ſatiſfaction for a firm, and laſting peace in his three Kingdomes, and was to come to <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> by agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to confirm them in ful Parliament. The Parliament having voted the Kings conceſſions ſatiſfactory, wherin his Majeſty, had given the ſubjects, more liberties, and freedomes in that treaty, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, then al the Kings ſince <hi>William</hi> the firſt, and afterwards the ſaid <hi>Cromwel</hi> with theſe Conſpirators, did expel moſt of the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, of the howſe of Commons, and impriſoned, them in Hel, and two common Inns, in the ſtrand, only leaving, ſuch other mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, in the howſe as were his Conſpirators and pentioners who ſold, their owne Conſciences, and the blood, lives, and liberties of the ſubject, by ſetting up a ſlaughter howſe (their high court of juſtice, a meer extrajudicial thing in law) on purpoſe to blood, and terrifie the people, and to ingroſs, the power, and wealth of the Kingdome to themſelves, and the Committee men: what waſt ſums of mony and plate, they have given to themſelves, it is partly in print, but far more concealed: and can ye expect juſtice from them who make themſelves judge and party, whoſe iron hands, you have ſufficiently felt: and afterwards openly committed that horrid, and Barbarous Act, a thing never parralleld in the world, many or moſt of them, now convened, in this Fleeting wood Parliament, being thoſe monſters, with there journy man <hi>Lentall</hi> the old Speaker (who correſponded, with the laſt King for his peace and aſſurance) that have brought al theſe miſeries upon the nation, and do now follow the ſame dictates
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:54740:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>of blood, and innovations: and if ye ſuffer them to fit, you muſt expect, nothing but blood, ruine of your eſtates, and deſtruction of the kingdom, by all illegal, and arbitrary waies whatſoever, and to ſel your remaining monuments of the kingdome, churches, and noble houſes, and put the money in what Purſes they pleaſe, and weaken the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom for a prey to a forraign Nation: Theſe will be like the 30. Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants of <hi>Athens,</hi> the <hi>Decemviri</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> you have felt their hands enough already, and will feel them again, more to purpoſe, if you let them ſit, who will call for any mans life and eſtate at their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures or diſpleaſures, whoſe Pride and power is to treaſure up un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous Mammon againſt the Day of Wrath: Their right to ſit is nothing but force and violence (a Monſter in nature) and a compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Theeves on the High way, calling a Councel in a Wood, and inlarging their unjuſt power by a Confederacy, have as much right to ſit in Councel, as theſe unſatiable Uſurpers, and may give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the name of Parliament as well as theſe: but all pious and truly affected to their country, hope theſe will prove a Fleeting Parliament as <hi>Fleetwoods</hi> Mock Parliament: The pact perſons of the Councel of War, with the old conſpiring Members of the kingdoms miſeries, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all Conſpiratots in this miſery for the nation, againſt Truth and Juſtice. That Parliament of which theſe were unruly and excremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Members, was abſolutely diſſolved by three waies: the force and violence upon the Houſe of Commons, by expelling and impriſoning their Members, and then the utter expulſion and extirpation of the reſt by <hi>Cromwel</hi> and his Conſpirators (many now ſitting, being part of them) which made that houſe <hi>ſine Die<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> and then the force and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence upon the Houſe of Lords, after adjournment to a Day, the mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Lords and their Speaker being prevented by the Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers guarding the Houſe (who writ upon it, This Houſe is to be Let) made it alſo <hi>ſine Die,</hi> a natural diſſolution: But the chief and main reaſon was the Kings death, a moſt abſolute diſſolution, who called them by his Writ to conſult with him, and where his Soul now is, it is feared many of them wil never come without great &amp; unfeigned Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. A Parliament is the great and free Councel of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, not called as this Juncto is, by the Speakers or other perſons, giving notice to one another for their meeting: but lawfully and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:54740:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>freely called and choſen, for the making and mending of Laws, for the ſubjects good, whereby they may have protection and ſecurity, conſiſting of King, Lords and Commons, whereunto the ſubject may have addreſs for his Grievances and redreſs of the ſame, fully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by Act of Parliament, of King Lords and Commons, the great ſecurity of the kingdom: And if the Judges and Miniſters of the Laws do not their Duties, they are loyable to legal judgements and ſentences, according to the diſmerrit of their offences. And <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> will never be happy without theſe Parliaments in Freedome, but otherwiſe moſt miſerable, as at this time you feel by experience. And while that long Parliament called by the King in Anno 1648. kept its integrety and ſincerity, God bleſſed it, but when it was cruel to its fellow Members, and unjuſtly intruded upon the King and kingdoms Rights, after full ſatisfaction given by his Majeſty, as the Bill paſſed for taking away the Star Chamber Court, and other offenſive Courts in the kingdom, Biſhops out of the Lords Houſe, and after that paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a Bill for a Triannual Parliament, and whatſoever elſe was for the kingdoms good, and offered the Parliament after wards only to treat with the Synod of Divines himſelf, or elſe for his Majeſty to chuſe 20 Divines to ſit amongſt them, for the ſettlement of the Diſcipline of the Church, as by his meſſage of the 20. of <hi>May,</hi> which 20. per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons could not overvote 120. or more: But by the Guilt and Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſome of the Parliament Members, when that Parliament made it ſelf a Court to tyrannize over its fellow ſubjects, their lives, liberties, and eſtates, and accumulate the wealth and treaſure of the kingdom to its ſelf,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd Pentioners to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>vel and their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ittee-men: God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>t low and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ble in the eyes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ple and at laſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>wn Members,</note> and its mercinary Members, to turn one another out of the Houſe; and will ye ſerve the ſcum and offile of that Parliament, that create themſelves a name and power without Law, Right, and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, whereby to murther your perſons, conſume your eſtates, and give you nothing but changes and uncertainties for ſecurity and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement. O <hi>England, England,</hi> repent, repent of all thy Perjury and breach of Faith with God and Man, of the breach of thy Allegiance thou haſt ſworn to thy lawfull King, and his Heyors after him ſworn unto, and declared to the whole World, by the Members of that Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and by theſe now ſitting at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and all the other ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Oaths, Vows, Covenants, Proteſtations and Declarations, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:54740:5"/>thereunto for the honour and happineſs of the King and king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, <hi>That you will with your Eſtates and Lives, mutually preſerve the Rights and Priviledges of Parliament, and Liberties of the kingdom, and Preſerve and Defend his Majeſties Perſon and Authority, that the World may bear witneſs with your Conſciences of your Loyalty, that you had no thoughts nor intentions, to diminish his Majeſties juſt Power and Greatneſs.</hi> O <hi>England, England,</hi> Repent, Repent of all the multiplication of Illegal Oaths and Engagements thou haſt taken, and never take any Illegal Oath more, although it ſeem never ſo religious; but ſuch as are confirmed by King and Parliament, the wholeſom and only lawfull conſtitution of the kingdom: you feel the event of illegal oaths well enough. And <hi>London</hi> the great Metropolis of the kingdom, ſell not your eſtates, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, lives and conſciences, as you do your wares and goods: you have done too much already, and make not your ſelves abominable to all ſucceeding generations: you could fight well enough to bring your ſelves into ſlavery, but not to free your ſelves out of it the time was when you had the prize in your hand and may yet, if ye will put on wiſedom and courage to redeem your honors, and your ſelves from ſlavery, and preſerve the rights and priviledges of Parliaments, and reſtore the King upon the principles of honor and juſtice, and for your own, and the kingdomes liberties and ſecurity: you had thoſe which ſtood in the gap for you, who thirſted to have hazarded their lives for your redemption, and their King and Country: But you ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered your ſelves to be cheated and betrayed into a Treaty, by two or three of your Aldermen, and ſome others, Citizens and Miniſters, who were <hi>Cromwels</hi> Factors, and betraied you, (as <hi>Iudas</hi> did Chriſt, or like <hi>Synon</hi> who brought in the Grecian horſe into <hi>Troy</hi>) when the power of the whole Army was not one quarter equivolent, to the power and ſtrength of the City; whereas if you would have defended your own and the Parliaments liberties, and maintained your Declarations (which you ſo unworthily recalled, as the Parliament alſo did theirs) moſt of the Army had come off to you, and this you were told by ſome of your very faithfull and good friends, and was there any appearance of blood, If you had not accepted the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage for acceptance of the treaty, by 6. of the Clock at night one day when the Army was at <hi>Turnam</hi> Green, and by <hi>Brainford,</hi> into which you were ſcarced by the long winded ſpeech of <hi>Cromwels</hi> meſſenger; the ſaid meſſenger telling the Common Councel, that if by 6, of the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:54740:6"/>Clock that night, <hi>Cromwel</hi> and his Officers of the Army, had not notice of your acceptanee of the Treaty, the Army would be inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in blood, with the City forces at the Forts, and it was 9. or 10. of the clock at night, before the meſſage was ſent from <hi>London,</hi> and the ſame long winded meſſenger returning again the next morning, to the Common Councel in <hi>London,</hi> from <hi>Cromwel,</hi> and his Complices who were then at <hi>Syon</hi> houſe, tould the Common Councel, that the night before, as he went to <hi>Syon</hi> houſe, that there was about half a troop of horſe, in an Inn in <hi>Knightbridge,</hi> and one Centinel in the ſtreet, and at <hi>Turnam</hi> Creen about one Regiment and half of Horſe, the Troopers all lying a ſleep, and their horſes feeding, tyed to the Troo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers legs, unleſs a Centinel or two in the high way, and that was about 10. or 11. of the clock at night, and what faith was to be given to that meſſenger, who ye knew, was the Cabals Creature of <hi>Cromwels</hi> and my Lord <hi>Says:</hi> If ye had ſent <hi>Cromwel</hi> word, that if he ſhot his Guns againſt the City you would Ring your Bels, as the Duke of <hi>Florence</hi> told <hi>Charles</hi> the 8. of <hi>France</hi> when his Army was before <hi>Florence,</hi> and then the Kings Army durſt not meddle with the City by which courage and Reſolution, the Duke preſerved the City and its liberties &amp; ſo might ye have preſerved <hi>London.</hi> Repent <hi>London,</hi> and Redeem the innocent blood that hath been ſpilt by your means, I ſay you could fight wel enough to inſlave your ſelves, but not to Redeem your loſt honor, which formerly you have long enjoyed: And until <hi>England</hi> return to its Loyalty, and its Iuſt Principles, for King and Parliament, it wil be like a man in a feaver, removing from one bed or Pallet to another, but never be at eaſe, or reſt, until the feaver hath left him. Why ſhould theſe new Fleeting wood Governors (ſo much hated) think to keep their intended Government, built upon the Principles of Injuſtice, Avarice, and Ambition, expect more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, then the former Protectorians, or other changes of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment have had, hath not God overthrown the former pretended Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers, who ſought their own Ambition, and power, under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the kingdomes Good, how many Changes and alterations have ye had ſince the laſt Kings death: and can <hi>England</hi> without Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, promiſe its ſelf more ſecurity then former Empires, and other Kingdomes have done, hath it not been conquered by Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, Saxons, Danes, and Normans, and are not <hi>Englands</hi> ſins as great now, nay greater then formerly: Is there not a Generall Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:54740:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>of Magiſtrates, miniſters, and people do not almoſt all ſerve for lucre and Gain, and dawb with untempered morter, and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters who would be accompted pious and Religious, Intitle God to their Dawbing ſins, againſt knowledge, only for wordly profit, and Pedantick honor: and may not <hi>England</hi> without Repentance, ſuck the dregs of Gods wrath, and make <hi>England</hi> in Concluſion, the moſt miſerable of the 3. nations: let then that ſtand, take heed leaſt they fall: it is a kingdom, more envied then affected, unleſs for its bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit; and if the pride, malice, fury and revenge, of Scotch, Iriſh, and Forrainers, fall on it, (from which God keep it) it may be harraced, with iron hands, and hearts, and your Children, friends, Neighbors and Country men, ſold into forraign plantations, and ſlavery with as little, or leſs mercy, or pitty, then ye have ſent and ſold your Neighbours, Countrey men, and brethren: Do not ye ſee in theſe alterations, how God doth viſit the ſins of the Parents upon their Children. Therefore as a good Phyſitian, and Chyrurgian, muſt know the diſeaſe and wound, before he can cure it, ſo Pardon the zeal of this pen, not intentionally to Corrode, but Heal, for without ſence of ſin, there can be no true repentance: but let not us ſay like <hi>Caine,</hi> and <hi>Iudas,</hi> our ſins are greater then God can forgive, for if we Repent, God will forgive, and if <hi>England</hi> return to its loyaltie, Iuſt Government, or lawfull obedience, it will be heartily forgiven, and then, it will be firmely ſetled, upon a ſure foundation, in its juſt liberties that King and people, may enjoy both their Rights, and a full oblivion of all that is paſt, firmely confirmed by the King in a free Parliament, the great ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rity of the kingdom all theſe late ways, being abſolutely Mutenous and Tumultuous: and are a very few perſons conſiderable to the good and happineſs of a Nation (who ſeduce the Souldiers, and others that would be good Subjects) who if they pleaſe, may ſecure and ſave themſelves, moſt of the Grand Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of that horrid death, and murther, God having Reſerved their Iudgments to himſelf: do not you now plainly preceive, that <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wells</hi> murthering the laſt King, and his fair and Religious pretences, for the Kingdomes Good, were only ſteps to get the Crown himſelf, and not finding in his life time all things concurring for his atcheive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof: yet after his death would have his Effigies, adorned with Trophies of the Regalia, the Crown, Globe, and Scepter: and theſe few perſons now, that contrive this new Government are
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:54740:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>only to make themſelves, <hi>Voces Plebi &amp; Magiſtri Plebi,</hi> making the Councell of State, to bring forth their Monſter: Their mock Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the God fathers, the Army their actors: and the people their porters and ſpectators, to receive the Bleſſing (from them) of <hi>Iſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>char,</hi> and themſelves enjoy the free Common wealth, of wealth, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, luxury, power, and Revenge, againſt whom they pleaſe: Do not ye ſee they begin, with <hi>Lentall</hi> their Speaker, to make him as abſolute Lord Chancellor, as ever any was before, and themſelves will follow in other places, being the Giving Parliament, one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And wheras in Monarchy you have one head, to reſort unto for Iuſtice, and if his miniſters fail they are Puniſhable by law, and Parliament; but where you have many to Reſort unto, it will be like the old ſaying of the Deans and Chapters come to them apart, they are all honeſt, but together they are very knaves, and ſo will theſe be. Have ye got any thing by your often Changes, but loſſe of your Blood and eſtates. O that <hi>England</hi> would vindicate its ſelf from thoſe blots and juſt aſpertions now upon it for its own honour, and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and terror of its no friends abroad, that it may have a firm and laſting peace within its ſelf, which it can never have, without its lawfull King. Never was <hi>England</hi> more happy in a King, then it will be in this Kings Reſtoration, whoſe nature cannot be a Tyrant, who thirſteth, to receive his ſubjects, into his Gracious Favour, and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily wiſheth the Good, and Proſperity of <hi>England</hi> in generall, and its Metropolis <hi>London,</hi> which now ſerveth its Chargeable Task-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters for the Avarice and Ambition of a very few perſons: your law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full King is an Engliſhman born, and in heart and Affection the ſame (although loving, and juſt to all his ſubjects) of whoſe Gracious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition and Princely parts, his Enemies muſt, and do Confeſſe, and for his mercy, let him Confeſs it, that the King pardoned in <hi>Scotland,</hi> who was ſent out of <hi>England,</hi> to murther his Majeſty, as he volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily Confeſſed himſelf, after his apprehenſion: and for his care of his Subjects, let his peaceable, and unhurtfull march to <hi>Worceſter</hi> with his Army, (by his Majeſties eſpecial Command) teſtifie, wherein the kingdome, received not the leaſt damage by it. The kingdomes Terms, may be honorable, gracious, and ſecure, with the King, who thirſteth to come unto the Crown, by the intereſt, and love of his own people. His Majeſty alſo hath two Royall Brothers to Confirm his ſubjects ſecurity: The world cannot equalize ſuch three Princes
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:54740:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>whoſe fame ſoundeth loud abroad, and do not think, but God which ſo miraculouſly preſerved his Majeſty in going to <hi>Scotland,</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in <hi>Scotland,</hi> in ſo many dangers and Caſualties, and alſo when two were ſent thither to murther him: and after the Defeat at <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter,</hi> God ſo miraculouſly delivered him, and ſent his Majeſty ſafe into France, in which eſcape he ſhewed more then Kingly Courage and Reſolution, and God which hath delivered the Duke of <hi>York</hi> in ſo many hazards, and deſperate Charges, and Dangers, in the field, wherin his Highneſs, hath performed to Admiration, and the Duke of <hi>Gloceſter</hi> who by eſpecial providence of God was ſent out of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> young (not out of <hi>Cromwels</hi> affection to his Highneſs, but fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his Title to the Crown, and the peoples affection to the Royall Family) who in the laſt aſſault before <hi>Dunkirck</hi> fought like a Prince, and never left his Royal brother the Duke of <hi>York</hi> a ſwords length, and how they charged, again and again, &amp; what ſervice they did there is well known, for ther Everlaſting honors: and do not believe but that Almighty God, had reſerved theſe three great Princes, for ſome great work: they are bone of your bone, and Fleſh of your Fleſh: and if <hi>England,</hi> will not be juſt to its ſelf, in doing juſtice where God requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth it God may be Graciuſly juſt, to their Lawfull King, who never offended <hi>England</hi> (but deſireth its good heartily and loveth it) and reſtore his Majeſty upon the injuſtice of a perjured nation: doubt not but in a general peace, there will be a conſideration for him by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Princes (who may be ſerved, as he now is, by their own ſubjects) whoſe Juſtice and right it is to be your <hi>K.</hi> have a care of the old <hi>Motto, ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſapit ingratus.</hi> Therefore <hi>England</hi> make it thy work alone, and have the honour and happineſs of it thy ſelf without thy neighbours: The King is your father, your country is your mother, and until father and mother be united, the family muſt be divided: And as he is your na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and only lawfull King, ſo no King under Heaven hath a clearer Title (moſt Kings not ſo clear) the Saxon, Norman, Engliſh, and Scotch Race, ſolely and wholly centring in his Maj. And if the armies by ſea and land are ſenſible of their own honors, profit, and advantage and ſecurity, and the kingdoms happineſſe, they will rather ſerve the King and kingdom then theſe Fleeting maſters, every day changing upon uncertainties, and upon this juſt ſettlement of King and people: Their Arrears will be payed and ſatisfied, and the Commanders and Souldiers imployed for the honor and advantage of the nation. And
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:54740:8"/>is it not more noble and beneficial for ye to be in a continual and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable imploiment, with the love of the kingdom, then upon theſe uncertainties ye now are in, with the kingdoms curſe: upon this juſt ſettlement of King and people, the diſcipline of our religion will be ſetled the neareſt way agreeable to divine Scripture truth, withall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to tender conſciences: your King, and his two royal brothers, are reformed Proteſtants (in which reformed religion, with Gods grace, they refolve to live and die) for which <hi>Rome</hi> is not their great friend: And upon this juſt ſettlement, oblivion of all errors will bee paſſed in free Parl, with full indempnity, the exceptions included with your own judgments, Eſtates comprimized and ſecured by Parl, his Maj. Court regulated, the Law rectified, the kingdoms abuſes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, Trade reſtored and enlarged, manufactures increaſed, Land improved, and a great part of the kingdoms charge taken off, mens minds ſetled in peace and quietneſs, and the people governed by law and love, penalties confirmed by Parliam, againſt diſtinction of nick names, whereby the nation may be brought into an amiable poſture and condition: and a full and perfect Act of amneſty and oblivion paſſed and confirmed by King and Parl. with invocation unto Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for its obſervance; and noble Acts advanced, for juſt and honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ends, for the honor and advantage of the nation: Experience having improved your King, and our Engliſh nation, by awaking them out of the drowſineſs of a ſlothfull and luxurious Peace. This Comenting at home of King and people, will prevent all forraign de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, and make us formidable and terrible abroad, and on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, by our diviſions indanger us, for a prey to other nations: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (again) <hi>England,</hi> have the honor of it thy ſelf without the help of thy neighbors, who brought thee into confuſion: And all ye loyal ſubjects of <hi>England,</hi> and excluded Members of the long Parl. by <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel,</hi> that were for the perſonal Treaty in the Iſle of <hi>Wight,</hi> and all ye Nobility, Gentry, Commonalty, Juſtices of Peace, Sheriffs of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral counties and ſhires, and all cities, and towns corporate, all Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates and Members of the kingdom whatſoever, who have all your rights from the Crown, your lawfull King and his Heyors, and that do enjoy your laws, liberties, francheſes and freedoms, from the conceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of King and free Parl, Riſe up, as <hi>Thraſibulus</hi> did againſt the 30. Tyrants of <hi>Athens,</hi> and as one man put your ſelves into a poſture of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, againſt any power whatſoever that ſhall invade your Rights
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:54740:8"/>and Liberties and debar ye of free Parl, which are your birth-rights and inheritance, and then treat with your King, from whom you may have honorable and ſafe conditions for the honor, happineſs, and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the nation, the children not bearing the ſins of their Parents, as in the Prophet <hi>Ezekel</hi>—and make your ſelves famous over all the world, to all poſterity: And unto the oppoſers of this happineſs and ſettlement, throw into their hearts and faces with invocation up to Heaven, <hi>the breach of all their Oaths, Vows, Covenants, Proteſtations and Declarations, for the honor and happineſſe of the King, for the freedom and Priviledges of Parliament, and for the good and liberty of the ſubject</hi> (as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutath</hi> the great Turk, did againſt <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ladiſlaus</hi> King of <hi>Hungary:</hi> The Time, and Covenant Breaker when his Army was almoſt loſt before his Invocation unto Heaven, and then gave him a wonderfull victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, over the Hungarians) that ye may be hereafter governed by law and not by the luſt of men, and be confident, God will bleſs ye in it and wil ſtrike ſuch a daunt, and terror into your Enemies hearts, that oppoſe your juſt and righteous Cauſe, that 10. of ye, ſhal chaſe an hundreth, and 100. of ye put 1000. to flight, but you muſt do it, with zeal, and dexterity, for all the Kingdome, to Riſe, as one Man, on one Day, and God bleſs ye in it. Ye have men enough to head ye: The protection and enjoyment, of your lawes, lives, liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Eſtates, being all taken from ye. Therefore ye muſt protect your ſelfes, as ye are bound, by the law of nature, that afterwards ye may have a free Parliament called, to ſettle, and confirm your laws, liberties and Eſtates: and in your riſing; uſe the people as Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and country men, not cruelly but kindly, and be ſure, ye are not created by independent treaties, nor long winded ſpeeches, let them ſeem never ſo religious (you have experience enough of that) untill you have a free Parliament choſen, not only to confirm your old <hi>Magna Carta,</hi> but to make a new <hi>Maxima Carta,</hi> Truth doth reſt, and is quiet, when its juſt ends are granted, but falſhood never: where is now <hi>Quintus Curtius,</hi> that ſtopt the Gulf of <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Scevola</hi> that loſt his hand to ſave the city: remember <hi>Siſia</hi> the noble Bohemian that defended <hi>Prage</hi> againſt the whole Imperial Army take but courage you have 9. parts of 10 of the Kingdome for ye: therefore O Engliſh Blood, and hearts, redeem your Liberties, and declare only for a free Parliament for the ſettlement of your laws, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, and Eſtates, (a moſt juſt cauſe and moſt ſafely may be Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:54740:9"/>with a good conſcience) and God bleſs and proſper ye in it, that his infinite Majeſty may have the honor and glory and the whole na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and your poſterity after ye, may have the benefit, and your ſelves of this age be engraven in everlaſting monuments, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorers, of your Kings and countries liberties, upon the Principles of Truth juſtice, mercy and amneſty; for ſo prayeth every true hearted Engliſh man.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed at London the <hi>12.</hi> of Iune <hi>1659.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
